<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Christian reprehension of confusion, ranterism, cruelty, and opposition to spiritual order and Christian liberty in brief reflections first on a conceited pamphlet untruly stiled Spiritual order and Christian liberty proved consistent in the Churches of Christ, and impositions upon the consciences of believers &amp;c. found antichristian and destructive to both, signed R.G. : secondly on A  brief history of the rise, growth, reign, supports, and suddain fatal foil of popery, and description of six popish pillars, by a hidden author / by G.W. and S.C.</title>
            <author>Whitehead, George, 1636?-1723.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1690</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 26 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 7 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A65851</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W1909</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R27590</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">09976822</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 09976822</idno>
            <idno type="VID">44421</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A65851)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 44421)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1346:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Christian reprehension of confusion, ranterism, cruelty, and opposition to spiritual order and Christian liberty in brief reflections first on a conceited pamphlet untruly stiled Spiritual order and Christian liberty proved consistent in the Churches of Christ, and impositions upon the consciences of believers &amp;c. found antichristian and destructive to both, signed R.G. : secondly on A  brief history of the rise, growth, reign, supports, and suddain fatal foil of popery, and description of six popish pillars, by a hidden author / by G.W. and S.C.</title>
                  <author>Whitehead, George, 1636?-1723.</author>
                  <author>S. C.</author>
                  <author>Crisp, Stephen, 1628-1692.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>12 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed and sold by A. Sowle,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1690.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>S.C. may be Stephen Crisp--NUC pre-1956 imprints.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>R. G. --  (Robert Gordon). --  Spiritual order and Christian liberty proved to be consistent in the Churches of Christ.</term>
               <term>Brief history of the rise, growth, reign, supports, and sodain fatal foyl of popery.</term>
               <term>Society of Friends --  Apologetic works.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:44421:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:44421:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A <hi>Chriſtian Reprehenſion</hi> OF Confuſion, Ranteriſm, Cruelty, and Oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition to <hi>Spiritual Order</hi> and <hi>Chriſtian Liberty,</hi> In Brief Reflections.</p>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> On a conceited Pamphlet, untruly Stiled, <hi>Spiritual Order and Chriſtian Liberty proved Conſiſtent in the Churches of Chriſt, and Impoſitions upon the Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences of Believers,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>found Antichriſtian and Deſtructive to both;</hi> Signed <hi>R. G.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> On a <hi>Brief Hiſtory of the Riſe, Growth, Reign, Supports, and ſuddain fatal foil of</hi> Popery; <hi>and Deſcription of Six Popiſh Pillars;</hi> By a hidden Author.</item>
            </list>
            <p>By Lovers of Truth and Peace, <hi>G. W.</hi> &amp; <hi>S. C.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Pſalm 10.</hi> verſ. <hi>8, 9.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>He ſitteth in the Lurking-Places of the Villages, in the Secret Places doth he Murder the Innocent; his Eyes are privily ſee againſt the Poor: He lieth in wait ſecretly as a Lyon in his Den, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>Printed and Sold by <hi>A. Sowle,</hi> at the <hi>Crooked-Billet</hi> in <hi>Holloway-Lane,</hi> in <hi>Shoreditch,</hi> 1690.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:44421:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:44421:2"/>
            <head>A <hi>Chriſtian Reprehenſion</hi> of Confuſion, Ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teriſm, Cruelty, and Oppoſition to <hi>Spiritual Order</hi> and <hi>Chriſtian Liberty,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <p>WHerein the Author of this Treatiſe has ſeemed to plead <hi>for Spiritual Order and Chriſtian Liberty, as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtent in the Churches of Chriſt, and againſt Impoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions on the Conſciences of Believers in Religious Practices, without in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Convincement or Clearneſs to act therein;</hi> and for <hi>the Principle of Immediate Inward Revelation of Light and Spirit,</hi> &amp;c. and againſt <hi>the Roman Church-Popes, &amp;c. uſurping Eccleſiaſtical Juriſdiction and Power unto an implicit and blind Obedience, Tyrannouſly uſurping and exerciſing Government over the Conſciences of Believers or Diſeiples,</hi> &amp;c. And yet that both <hi>Spiritual Order &amp; Chriſtian Liberty were eſtabliſhed by the Apoſtles in the firſt Churches,</hi> pag. 5. and for <hi>Church-Government, which is Spiritual,</hi> pag. 9. <hi>And that it reſts in the Power of any one per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Church to make Orders, for the better governing of the Church, ſo as in the Exerciſe of Church-Government the Rules of Expediency, Peace and Charity be obſerved,</hi> page 10. <hi>And that Spiritual Government and Chriſtian Liberty are not only Conſiſtent, and accordingly practiſed in the firſt Churches, but alſo neceſſary for preſerving Spiritual <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity and Peace of the Churches from Confuſion and Tyranny, all things be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing decently and in order, in Charity, and to Edification,</hi> pag. 6.</p>
            <p>With many more paſſages, which in themſelves being general Truths, we ſhould have let paſs the ſaid Treatiſe or Pamphlet without taking this notice of it, if the Author had not perverted and contradicted the ſame Truths by ſome perticular corrupt paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages and perverſe Reflections, and putting forth a ſting of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy and Bitterneſs in the Tail or Poſtſcript of his Pamphlet againſt the <hi>Quakers</hi> eſpecially, and tauntingly, and enviouſly telling of being <hi>alarmed with the loud Clamour of Church-Government, Laws, Orders of general and perticular Meetings of the Friends of the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry and others, the neceſſity of one or more in the Church having Power infallibly to determine all matters Controverted therein, to whom all muſt ſubmit, though unconvinced or unclear in themſelves, or elſe be
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:44421:3"/>branded with the odious Names of Schiſmatick,</hi> &amp;c. p. 2. By all which it appears the man's wholly ignorant of the Intent, Uſe and Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of thoſe general and perticular Meetings of our Friends, which he ſcornfully and enviouſly ſmites at. He falſly Clamours herein, for they have no Church-Government, Laws or Orders now to ſet up, being long ſince eſtabliſhed by the Lord's Power and Council; nor do they meet to determine all Controverſies in them, having no Controverſie either in Doctrine or Diſcipline to determine, the Lord having fully ſatisfied them in thoſe things by his Light and Spirit; nor yet to impoſe any matters upon any of their Society unconvinced or unclear therein; But for the help and comfort of one another in the love of God, and Unity of his bleſſed Spirit, in all things proper to ſuch Meetings, which are not for Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſie, nor to ſet up men over the Churches of Chriſt, but for the help and comfort of one another in the Lord, who is our Law-giver, from whom true Wiſdom and Counſel comes, whoſe Preſence and Power attends thoſe our Meetings, and is livingly felt in them; and therefore we value not what Envy and Scorn can ſay againſt them in this or any other perverſe Gain-ſayers, Apoſtates or others.</p>
            <p>We being willing to ſearch what are thoſe <hi>Impoſitions on Believers Conſciences?</hi> What thoſe <hi>Church-Orders, Laws, out ward Appointments, Inſtructions, New Papacy,</hi> &amp;c. which he conplains of and derides, as impos'd without inward convincement among the people called <hi>Quakers,</hi> at whom he Smites? Whether evil or unlawful in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, or altogether unneceſſary? We would know what perticu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar order or outward appointments <hi>&amp;c.</hi> they are, all his Clam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour is againſt? upon the ſearch we find them mentioned, and (as he conceits) ſtrongly argued againſt, page 7. 8. thus, viz.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The contradiction between, this kind of Impoſition and Immediate Revelation of the Light and Spirit of God in every Individual as his uner<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Rule, &amp;c. is in this, that this inward Revelation is aſſerted, as being of it ſelf ſufficient, if obeyed, to lead into all Truth, without any neceſſity of hearkening unto any outward Writings or Inſtructions whatſoever; but as this Light leads thereunto, which if it be ſo, that a Society be united upon that Principle, the uſeleſneſs of general or perticular outward Laws, and Inſtructions, and of the fore-appointed ſtanding Meetings Weekly, Monthly and Quarterly, and the frequenting the Set-Time and Places of thoſe Meetings, further than it becomes neceſſary to every indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidual Perſon of that Society through the Immediate Revelation in his own
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:44421:3"/>perticular then received, is ſo very Manifeſt, that indeed it is a deſerting the Caſe of Immediate Revelation, and an Acknowledgement of the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſufficiency of that Light within,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>This is ſuch an Argument and Oppoſition as we have ſcarce ever ſeen before, that becauſe the Light within, and Immediate Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation is ſufficient to lead into all Truth, therefore all outward Writings and Inſtructions whatſoever, for appointed ſtanding Meetings, Weekly, Monthly, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and frequenting them at ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times and places, are all uſeleſs to them of the ſame Communion; we deny the Conſequence.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> becauſe the Light of Chriſt within hath directed, or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered and ſetled ſuch a Method and Order for theſe our Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons Meetings, at Set-Times and Places, to be known, open and free, both to them that are in Chriſtian Society with us, and others who are ſeeking after the Truth; and not to leave them in uncertainties, as to Time and Place, when the Method is already ſetled as to both, in God's Wiſdom by his Light and Spirit, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the primitive Chriſtians Practice, who profeſt and knew the ſame Light and Spirit of Inward and Immediate Revelati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on as we profeſs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> When the Lord has taught us our duty, and order of our Chriſtian Meetings and Society, for us to perſevere in, we have our Law &amp; Order therein Eſtabliſhed by our great Law-giver, which to decline and reject, in pretence of leaving every one to an Immediate Revelation, when and where to meet, or to run up and down the Countries to gather every perticular Meeting; this were to tempt the Lord, and to ſlight his Law and Order already given and eſtabliſhed among us, under pretence of expecting a New Revelation for every Meeting, both as to time and place; and what intolerable cumber and trouble would this create?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> How, or where can this Gain-ſayer prove, that ever the Primitive Chriſtians, who knew Immediate Revelation and Light within, did keep their publick Meetings, either for Worſhip, Order or Diſcipline, without any ſore-appointment, of fet-time or places? If they did not, then the ſaid argument and conſequence reflects on them as well as on us.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> To ſuppoſe the ſufficiency of in ward Revelation to make all Writings or Inſtructions whatſoever uſeleſs, is to render all Goſpel-Preaching and Inſtructions by Immediate Revelation uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:44421:4"/>and unneceſſary, whether it be to the Church or others: And therefore this Writer, <hi>R.G.</hi> his arguing thus falaciouſly, to diſſolve our Chriſtian Meetings from their ſettlement as to Times and Places, and to make the Goſpel Miniſtry therein void; this is meerly idle, looſe and licentious, only ſuiting the Irreligious, the Care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, the looſe <hi>Ranters</hi> and ſlaviſh <hi>Temporizers,</hi> who dare not ſtand nor appear for Truth in perſecuting times; and what then is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come of his <hi>Spiritual Order</hi> he pleads for? We can't but obſerve the Man's Confuſion and Contradiction, whileſt ſometimes he pleads for Believers to be <hi>in the ſame mind and Judgment,</hi> to obſerve the Scriptures, <hi>and the Spiritual Order and Chriſtian Liberty</hi> Eſtabliſhed by the Appoſtles; and confeſſeth <hi>that indeed <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niformity in a Chriſtian Society is much to be deſired,</hi> page 3. 5. Yet in contradiction to all this, he pleads for ſuch a Latitude as that <hi>in ſeveral diſtinct Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhips, and differing in outward Practices, they ought to continue as one in the Lord,</hi> Page 1. <hi>And for Church-<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity, no Schiſm in the Body, Chriſtians to be of one mind in the Lord, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity in Spirit, not in an <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niformity of outward Practices,</hi> Page 4. And yet that <hi>indeed <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nifor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity in a Chriſtian ſociety is much to be deſired:</hi> Thus confuſed and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradictory ſaying and unſaying this Agent appears; and while he contends ſo much for Charity, Love and Unity of Spirit, &amp;c. in diſtinct outward Practices, ſeveral diſtinct Fellowſhips, &amp;c. He miſerably diſſembles and plays the Hippocrite, whilſt he is enviouſly ſmiting againſt the Chriſtian Society of the People called <hi>Quakers,</hi> becauſe they differ from him, and cannot allow themſelves ſuch a Liberty as his looſe arguing (like the <hi>Ranters</hi>) tends to, going on like them, telling of <hi>what ever outward diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſation of Light God hath once gloriouſly appeared in; the Life of God in every outward Adminiſtration, is one and the ſame Adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, being but the outward Garment that he chuſeth and refuſeth at his pleaſure, gathering his People out of various Adminiſtrations into himſelf, who is Love, however diſtinguiſhed from one another, who therefore cannot be tyed to any one Form,</hi> Page. 14. But pray where doth he prove that either the diſpenſation of Light, wherein God Gloriouſly appeareth, or the outward Adminiſtration wherein his Life is, in the Goſpel diſpenſation, is refuſed, or the Form of God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs rejected by the Lord, or his People in the Goſpel Diſpenſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion? This Perſon's Work againſt us ſtill tends to <hi>Ranteriſm,</hi> under pretence of <hi>Love and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion,</hi> not diſtinguiſhing between the admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtration
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:44421:4"/>of the Law, and the Diſpenſation of the Goſpel; and tho' he does ſo greatly pretend to <hi>Love and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion of the whole Iſrael of God, walking under various outward Practices, becauſe of differing Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſions,</hi> yet he is ſo far from either Love or Chriſtian Charity, that he ſhews neither towards the People called <hi>Quakers,</hi> whom in his Poſtſcript he bitterly Reproaches, telling of the <hi>Builders of</hi> Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon, <hi>this Beaſt deſcribed,</hi> Rev. 13. <hi>among the Quakers, comparing them to Sect Mrs Form-Builders, Proud and Self-Righteous</hi> Phariſees <hi>of this People,</hi> &amp;c. Thus the Serpent's ſting and venom appears in the Tail of his Work; thus he has vented his confuſion and envy, like a Babel Builder, againſt the Innocent whom the Lord ſtands by; one while he is for Order, Government, Form and Uniformity in a Chriſtian Society; another while he is againſt it and them, who are ſtedfaſt in that Chriſtian Order and Form the Lord has gather<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them into, and his Preſence and Power ſupports them therein, who are neither for making Rents, Schiſms, nor Sect, Maſters, but teſtifie againſt them, in the Name of their Lord and Maſter Chriſt Jeſus. And though this falſe Accuſer has oppoſed the Impoſition of Laws and Orders upon Chriſtians Conſciences, without in ward Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincement, yet he appears very defective and Partial, in that he has not given Teſtimony againſt making Oppoſition and Parties againſt ſuch Order and Church-Government, as is agreed upon by a Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Society in the Truth; for it's ſuch oppoſition, cauſing Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions and Seperations, which <hi>We,</hi> as a Chriſtian Society can in no ways own, nor Countenance, but Teſtifie againſt in whomſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver that profeſſing the ſame Divine Light and Truth and Imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate Revelation as we do. And the Lord Rebuke all our envious Oppoſers.</p>
            <p>After this ſecret Smiter has thus diſſorderly argued againſt Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, he gives us this falſe and ſcornful Wipe, viz. <hi>This little Now Erected Popery,</hi> Page 8. but no Demonſtration, nor Manifeſt Proof thereof againſt us, other than what himſelf hath granted and aſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to; nor has he proved the People (whom he chiefly Smites at) juſtly chargable with Popery, or <hi>Raiſing old Arguments out of the Rubbiſh of Popery to defend it.</hi> But thus Smits blindfold in the dark; for we raiſe no Arguments, but what are warrantable by the Holy Scriptures of the Old and New Teſtament.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:44421:5"/>
               <p>I Having lately ſeen a Pamphlet, called, <hi>A Hiſtory of the Riſe, Growth, Reign, Supports and ſuddain fatal foil of Popery, with a Deſcription of its Six Pillars:</hi> I looked for the Hiſtoriographer's Name, but find that concealed in Darkneſs, he being conſcious to himſelf it would not abide the Light and that if his Name had been expoſed, then his Folly and Raſhneſs would have reflected upon his Perſon: So he has left us to the old Rule, to know the Tree by the Fruits.</p>
               <p>The firſt thing he ſeems to reflect upon is Railing Accuſations, which in Words he highly explodes, and ſays, <hi>Its the duty of</hi> Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians <hi>to perform all Offices of Good to their Country, with utmoſt Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, &amp;c.</hi> So that we might expect a mighty ſober and charitable account of things from this Man by his beginning; but alas, the Man had not writ much before the Venom of his Spirit appears againſt all ſorts of People differing from his own Sentiments, and lays about him like a Fury, calling one ſort of People <hi>pernicious to Church and State;</hi> Another ſort <hi>Paganiſh, damnable Hereticks, void of Conſcience.</hi> And in pag. 11. ſpeaks his mind out at once, viz. <hi>That its the Magiſtrates duty to puniſh all ſorts of Diſſenters, from the old Councils and Canons with the ſame Puniſhment with which they puniſh Murderers and Adulterers, and not at all to tolerate them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>By this time we ſee what is the ground of his Anger, that makes him buſle thus, the <hi>Anabaptiſts, Presbyterians, Independents</hi> and <hi>Quakers</hi> are not hanged a days for being ſuch; as Murderers are; but what ſort of Man this is, may eaſily be gueſt at, and upon In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiry, we ſhall find him a Stone in the Building of the ſixth Pillar of <hi>Popery,</hi> viz. a <hi>Popiſh Church-man,</hi> retaining in him ſome of the worſt Dregs of <hi>Popery,</hi> viz. Cruel Perſecutions unto Death; for all ſuch as he is pleaſed to brand with <hi>Hereſie</hi> or <hi>Schiſm,</hi> which all <hi>Proteſtants</hi> look upon as the avowed Principle of <hi>Papiſts;</hi> and ſo it ſeems it is his: And it was he, or ſuch Church-men as he is, that were the Cauſe of ſuch Cruelties and Barbarities upon account of Religion here in <hi>England</hi> from the Years 1680. to 1686. In which they ſet the Informers a work to Ruin many Hundred good Families in this
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:44421:5"/>Kingdom, and filled the Goals with fourteen or fifteen Hundred Innocent Priſoners, who ſuffered under their Cruelties as Tro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phies of the great Power and Rule that the <hi>Popiſh</hi> Church-men had in thoſe days; I ſay, <hi>Popiſh</hi> Church-men, for the real or mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Church-men do generally excuſe themſelves of that work, as much as they can, and do deny Perſecution for Conſcience-ſake to be any Principle of their Church, and do lay the Fault upon ſuch bloody Hunters and Drivers as this Hiſtory-man, who while they ſeemed to be Members of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> by their Cruelty and Feircneſs againſt <hi>Diſſenters,</hi> brought this Ignominy upon their Church, and put an oppertunity into the Hand of a <hi>Popiſh King;</hi> when he came to eaſe the heavy Burdens which they had ſo Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elly laid on, and to put a ſtop to the Ruinous Practices of the wicked Informers (which they had made the Pillars and Supporters of their Church) as a <hi>Great Father</hi> of their Church being told, what a ſhame the Informers were to his Church, ſaid, <hi>That a Ship could not be built without ſome crooked Wood;</hi> implying the Ravenous Informers as neceſſary to the uphold, or building the Church, as crooked Wood to building a Ship) and thereby to Ingratiate him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in the Hearts of the greateſt part of the Kingdom, by the eaſe he gave them, either from their Sufferings, as <hi>Diſſenters,</hi> or from the Slavery and Drudgery they lay under, as Officers in their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpective Places, being all at the Call and Command of thoſe wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Varlets, to Ruin their honeſt Neighbour, how, when, and where they pleaſed to Require them.</p>
               <p>Now after they had, I ſay, provided ſuch a Means for the <hi>Popiſh King</hi> to Ingratiate himſelf, and if poſſible, to ſweeten the Minds of his Subjects into a better Opinion of him and his Government, then they had conceived; he took hold of the oppertunity given, and in a good meaſure emptied the Goals, ſtopt the Informers Trade; cauſed ſome to be puniſhed for their notorious Perjury; others fled for it; and then he put out a Declaration, to ſtop ſuch Cruel Proceedings, till Remedy might be found for all People to have a legal right to Worſhip God, as they were perſwaded was moſt acceptable to him; as of right they ought.</p>
               <p>But when theſe poor <hi>Diſſenters</hi> were thus delivered by a <hi>Popiſh King,</hi> from their <hi>Proteſtant Fetters,</hi> then thoſe (pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended) <hi>Preteſtant Perſecuters</hi> grew exceeding angry, both with him, and with the <hi>Diſſenters</hi> that he had ſet at Liberty; and
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:44421:6"/>fain would they be at the Old Trade again if they could: But becauſe their Horns are ſhortned for goring that way, now they are trying other ways to bring miſchief upon us; and becauſe he thinks the beſt way in theſe Times to bring Suffering upon us, is to ſet us forth as <hi>Supporters of Popery,</hi> and thinks there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to raiſe up a <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Zeal againſt us; for it may be he thinks others as much void of Senſe, and as much ſubject to Blood &amp; Enmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty as himſelf; for they muſt be very ſilly that will be kindled by his falacious way of Argument into bitterneſs againſt us: For Example; He affirms the poor <hi>Quaker</hi> to be one of the <hi>Pillars of Popery;</hi> but when we go to ſeek for demonſtration; why, they addreſt <hi>King James:</hi> Ay, but what did they ſay? They returned their Grate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Acknowledgements for the Eaſe and Freedom they Enjoyed, from their Cruel Perſecutions the <hi>Popiſh</hi> part of the <hi>Church of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> had laid upon them; and humbly deſired he would go on to eaſe them from the Grievances and Oppreſſions that ſtill lay upon their tender Conſciences.</p>
               <p>Now let all Rational Men judge, whether this hath any the leaſt ſavour of ſupporting <hi>Popery;</hi> might not as much have been ſaid to the <hi>Grand Senior,</hi> if lie had been Regnent here, without any juſt cauſe to impute <hi>Turkiſm</hi> to them? And doth not this bold da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring Man at the ſame time, ſpit his Venom againſt all the <hi>Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men,</hi> pertaining to the ſeveral <hi>Inns of Court,</hi> and againſt moſt of the <hi>Grand-Jury-Men,</hi> and <hi>Corporations,</hi> among whom I know there be <hi>better Proteſtants</hi> than he is: but who is ſo bold as <hi>blind Bayard?</hi> And how much cauſe hath this man to Rage againſt us after this furious rate, to tell the World we are a <hi>Pillar of Popery, Paganiſh, Men without any Conſcience, damnable Hereticks,</hi> &amp;c. pag. 22, 23. But in the Concluſion of that Paragraph (through forgetfulneſs, or ſome other ill Accident) the man pulls down all this fiery Pile about his own Ears, and tells us, That theſe <hi>Quakers</hi> would not Vote for the New Members in <hi>London,</hi> for fear they might be In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrumental to bring in <hi>King James</hi> again.</p>
               <p>Can any Man that is in his Sences, think this <hi>Hiſtory-maker</hi> was in his, when he blundred out this <hi>Nonſence;</hi> which if put toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther reads thus, The <hi>Quakers</hi> are one of the Pillars of <hi>Popery,</hi> for they would not Vote for the New Members, for fear they ſhould bring in <hi>King James</hi> again; and it is even as good <hi>Logick</hi> to ſay, the <hi>Quakers</hi> are a Pillar of <hi>Popery,</hi> for they thankfully acknowledged
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:44421:6"/>a Popiſh King's kindneſs, for delivering them from Cruel <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants, Popiſh Perſecution.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But after all this, methinks I find more cauſe to ſuſpect this <hi>Hiſtoriographer</hi> to be himſelf really Guilty of what he would faſten upon others, namely <hi>ſupporting</hi> and <hi>upholding Popery;</hi> for he is one that would in a hidden, ſly way <hi>Advance Popery;</hi> for he gives it ſuch Magnitude in his Hiſtory (which he tranſmits to futer Ages) as I believe the moſt Arrogant <hi>Jeſuite</hi> in <hi>France</hi> would not have dared to do; For <hi>(mark)</hi> he hath preſented ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry near all the People of <hi>England,</hi> ſave a piece of the <hi>Church of England,</hi> to be in the Intereſt of <hi>upholding</hi> and <hi>ſupporting Popery;</hi> for if <hi>Anabaptiſts, Presbyterians, Quakers, Independants,</hi> and <hi>part of the Church of England,</hi> be all concerned, (as he ſaid) how doth he think a piece of the <hi>Church</hi> ſhould grapple with the other piece; and all the other Intereſts beſides? So that it ſeems to me as if his buſineſs or task were (whoever ſet him to work) to ſhew the People of this and other Nations, the <hi>Popiſh Intereſt</hi> in a Mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplying-Glaſs; That if they will not love, yet they may at leaſt fear it; and to make the <hi>Proteſtant Intereſt</hi> very diminitive: This is not like one that wrote in <hi>King Jame's</hi> days, that there were not Papiſts enough in <hi>England</hi> to make all the <hi>Coal-Fires</hi> in <hi>London</hi> at once. But if this Hiſtory-man be to be credited, the <hi>Popiſh Intereſt</hi> muſt be looked upon very formidable ſtill, for Five of his Six Pillars are ſtill what they were; and four of them are more firmly ſettled than they were then; by the Act of King and Parliament for eaſe of tender Conſciences, by which it appears the Government and Wiſdom of the Kingdom did not ſee with this man's Eyes; they did not think it the beſt way to hang people for diſſenting (in ſome points of <hi>faith</hi> or <hi>worſhip</hi>) every Circuit and Aſſizes, as Murderers commonly are ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved. And truly it is hard for a man of his <hi>evil temper</hi> to retain ſo much <hi>venom</hi> in himſelf, but he muſt vent it againſt ſome body; and I perceive the Government ſhould have a ſnare of it if he durſt; but <hi>curſt Cows have ſhort Horns:</hi> He reflects what he durſt upon the Magiſtrate, page 11. for not doing their duty, namely in not <hi>hanging up all</hi> that diſſent from any of the <hi>Canons</hi> of the firſt <hi>ſix,</hi> or at leaſt four <hi>general Councils,</hi> as they do <hi>murderers.</hi> But if this man would come into the Light, we might ſee him; I am perſwaded it would be
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:44421:7"/>eaſie to prove him a <hi>diſſenter</hi> from ſeveral of the <hi>Canons</hi> of theſe very <hi>Councils;</hi> but I would not have him hanged for it, but live and learn to be <hi>wiſer,</hi> and <hi>honeſter,</hi> and to repent him of his Raſhneſs, and learn to love his Neighbours, and not thus <hi>Cain</hi>-like, to grudge the Rain and Sun-ſhine to men of better Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples than himſelf, and perhaps (when we know him) they will out-do him in Practice and Converſation alſo. However, I mean to leave him at preſent, with the Exhortation of an Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erring Teacher, <hi>Whatſoever you would that Men ſhould do unto you, do ye unto them;</hi> and then he will write no more Books, to procure his Neighbours to be hanged for Conſcience-ſake, till he is willing to be Hanged himſelf upon the ſame ſcore.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:44421:7"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
